<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>git on Raphael Brugier</title>
    <link>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/tags/git/</link>
    <description>Recent content in git on Raphael Brugier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 22:34:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.raphael-brugier.com/tags/git/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Fix the Git completion with Oh-my-Zsh on Mac</title>
      <link>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/fix-git-completion-zsh-mac-homebrew/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 22:34:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/fix-git-completion-zsh-mac-homebrew/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/my-development-environment/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I have explained how I have setup oh-my-zsh with the git plugin.
I am also using homebrew to manage the packages installed on my Mac.
After upgrading Git recently, I have noticed the Git completion was not as powerful anymore.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Add a Git hook to automatically verify a repository&#39;s email</title>
      <link>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/git-verify-email-hook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 13:40:15 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/git-verify-email-hook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I use Git a lot and I often have to switch between my personal repositories (ie: Github) and my professional (Ippon) repositories on the same laptop.
My default Git email is configured to my personal email and I have often forgotten to configure it to my professional email when creating/cloning a repository for my company.
Like everything in Git, this can be automated to avoid mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I will show how I use a Git hook to check the email configured in any repository before every commit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My development environment</title>
      <link>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/my-development-environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 18:02:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/my-development-environment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A customized development environment could be a huge productivity boost in the day to day work.
In this post, I will share the tools and configurations I currently use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>git commit fixup</title>
      <link>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/git-commit-fixup/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 18:37:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.raphael-brugier.com/blog/git-commit-fixup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this article, I will describe a git option to quickly fix a previous commit.
This sometimes happens when I want to fix a typo in a previous commit after few new commits.
The goal is to keep a &amp;ldquo;clean&amp;rdquo; git history with consistent commits adding features to facilitate the code reviews.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>